Fatih SAYIN

Austin, TX 78729 | fmsayin@hotmail.com| (512) 765 3221 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

A strategic, multidisciplinary data analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perspective. Five year of previous expertise on research and data analytics combined with the best creative data visualizations, actionable insights, and approximation algorithms available. Experience with the tools such as VBA, Python, Ipython, Pandas, SQL, MongoDB, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn, and PySpark.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Queries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Tableau

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib,
- API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet

MOST RECENT PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

- Name: Machine Learning Real Estate Project (The Relationship between Stock Market & Real Estate Price)
- **Description:** The purpose of this project was to build a real-estate pricing model with a dataset which we gathered from Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT). In this project 8 popular machine learning models were used, such as Decision Tree Regression, Random Forest Regression, K Nearest Neighbors Regression, Support Vector Machine, Ridge Regression, XGBoost, Lasso Regression, Baseline Model.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Machine-Learning-Real-Estate-Project

- Name: Rental Movie Database
- **Description:** Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected. Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub **Link:** https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql_challange
- Name: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects Data Analysis
- Description: Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign. Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DATA ANALYST

Cosmos Trading Inc., Austin, Texas, USA / January 2019 - Present

- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and as well as VLOOKUP function
- Created Business Intelligence (BI) solutions, analytical dashboards and tools for business users in Tableau
- Created daily reports in designed Excel spreadsheet with pivot tables
- Gathered business requirements and converted it into SQL stored procedures for database specific projects
- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the executive board to make the correct decisions
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Perform weekly and monthly reviews and analyses of current processes using operational metrics and reports
- Validated resource requirements and develop cost estimate models
- Prepared technical reports by collecting, analyzing and summarizing information and trends
- Researched, planed, recommended and implemented dashboards and data visualization in Tableau to meet the organization's business requirements
- Analyzing data from particular stock market movements. Used pandas to get stock market information for visualization

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Freelance, Austin, Texas, USA / August 2016 - December 2018

Completed some social projects as a freelance researcher and analyst

- **Used tools for all these projects:** Python, pandas, numpy, matplotlib, seaborn, beautiful soup for web scraping, MySQL and SQL queries and scripts, data import/export (various platforms).
- Name: Effects of unsuccessful coup attempt happened on July 15th, 2016 in Turkey
- **Description**: After the military coup attempt, 4 million individuals were affected (500 650 individuals were arrested, 2285 educational Institutions, 1600 NGOs, 189 media outlets and 15 universities were shut down). Each institution and occupational group data were analyzed.
- Name: Election Data Project Polls (2016 General Election: Trump vs. Clinton)
- **Description**: In this data project I will be looking at data from the 2016 election. In this project I will analyze the results of political polls. I will analyze this aggregated poll data and answer some questions.
- Name: Refugee Migration
- **Description**: Every year, hundreds of thousands of individuals get away their countries as refugees because of their country condition. I will be analyzing where these refugees get away from, the country they settle in, and the potential impact on the countries accepting these individuals.
- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (Euro League)
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs. GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP.

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Basari University Research Center, Samsun, TURKEY / September 2014 - July 2016

- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the university executive board to make the correct decisions
- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Used statistical techniques for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Analyzed academic evaluations to report to the university senate and set achievable academic goals
- Wrote academic research, made informed recommendations, managed the planning and development of design and procedures of metrics reports for short and long terms